Guide to the Thomas Lee Settle Papers, 1795-1949 RL.01168
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Thomas Lee Settle papers
1795-1949
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Settle, Thomas Lee, 1836-1920
RL.01168
10 Linear Feet
Physician and Confederate surgeon, of Paris (Fauquier Co.), Va. Alleged to have pronounced the death of abolitionist John Brown. Correspondence, travel journal, bills, presecriptions, deeds, receipts, records of land sales, and other papers (chiefly 1820-1900), concerning Settle's medical career, his interests in stock raising and farming, Civil War, events in Virginia (1861-1862), the Confederate medical service, activities of military units, and other matters. Includes letters from Robert H. Simpson, an offcer of the 17th Virginia Infantry.
5,641 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Thomas Lee Settle Papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1955.
Biographical Note
Physician and Confederate surgeon, of Paris (Fauquier Co.), Va. Alleged to have pronounced the death of abolitionist John Brown.
Collection Overview
Papers of Thomas Lee Settle (1836-1920), physician, and surgeon of the 11th Virginia Cavalry, C.S.A., include orders for the Virginia militia, 1797 and 1800; family letters to Texas, Missouri, and Tennessee; and correspondence concerning the education of the Settle children and friends at various schools and academies in Virginia, and at Virginia Military Institute, Lexington, Virginia. Civil War correspondence, including letters of Captain Robert H. Simpson and other Confederate soldiers, describes the battles of first Manassas, Chickahominy Swamp, and Fredericksburg, the Peninsular Campaign, crops and conditions in northern Virginia during the war, and directions for making salt. There are also records of land sales, deeds, and rent receipts; medical correspondence, prescriptions, and bills; bills and receipts for land transactions, household expenses, and apple brandy making; horse-dealing records during the Civil War; two Confederate Loan Bonds; business papers of A. H. Settle & Co., merchants of Paris, Virginia, medical diary, 1855-1858, 1861, and 1865-1866, of Thomas Lee Settle; and a diary, 1863-1864, of Thomas Lee Settle describing his activities as surgeon to the 11th Virginia Cavalry. A journal, 1863, of John S. Timberlake entitled "Trip to Florida and Salt Works, Oct. 20, 1863. With descriptions of the country and other particulars intervening on the way," contains detailed descriptions of various salt works in Georgia; "Descriptions of Florida and Health and Other Particulars (useful) as they Happen" discussing health and agricultural conditions, sugar making, and the economic conditions of Florida and Georgia plantations; and a synopsis of Adiel Sherwood's 1860 Gazetteer of Georgia. Postwar materials include Sunday school record book, 1884; letters from soldiers in the Spanish-American War discussing camp life in Florida, the Rough Riders, courts-martial, and desertion; letter, 1909, from T. C. Evans, dean of the Medical Department, University of Louisville, Louisville, Kentucky discussing his department; letters from Edgar Ackley Moore (d. 1924), physician, to his wife Pauline (Settled Moore, daughter of Thomas Lee Settle, while serving in the U.S. Army Medical Reserve Corps during World War I, describing camp life and his experiences in America and France, the work of the Young Men's Christian Association and the American National Red Cross in France, casualties, prisoners, hospitals, and physicians; papers relating to Moore's Masonic affiliation; ledger, 1905-1907, and accounts, 1906-1912, of Edgar Ackley Moore; literary reviews; medical pamphlets; and scrapbooks and exercise books. Volumes consist of medical visiting and account books, 1855-1914, commonplace books, 1852-1867, daybook, 1901-1905, expense book, 1870-1880, ledgers, 1867-1913, and record book, 1856-1857, of Thomas Lee Settle; account book for the John Horn estate; pamphlets, including one on the San Francisco earthquake of 1906 and another on a silver mining scheme in Canada, entitled Julian Hawthorne and Company (1909); a stallion service book; and photographs. Other papers include genealogical information, original poetry, and legal documents and wills.
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal narratives, Confederate; Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Physicians -- Virginia -- Fauquier County; Real property -- Virginia; Agriculture -- Virginia; Livestock -- Breeding; Confederate States of America -- Army -- Surgeons; Confederate States of America -- Army -- Virginia Infantry Regiment, 17th; Confederate States of America -- Army -- Sanitary affairs; Simpson, Robert H., d. 1864; Settle, Thomas Lee, 1836-1920
- Thomas Lee Settle Papers, 1795-1949, 18 boxes
  - Papers, 1794-1876 (Box 1)
  - Papers, 1877-1888 (Box 2)
  - Papers, 1889-1893 (Box 3)
  - Papers, 1894-1904 (Box 4)
  - Papers, 1905-1911 (Box 5)
  - Papers, 1912-1919 (Box 6)
  - Papers, 1920-1929 (Box 7)
  - Papers, 1930-1955 and undated. (Box 8)
  - Papers, undated. (Box 9)
  - Legal Papers, 1772-1951 (Box 10)
  - School Reports, 1885-1890 (Box 10)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 10)
  - Printed Materials (Box 10)
  - Medical Papers (Box 10)
  - Miscellany (Box 10)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1770-1869 (Box 11)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1870-1877 (Box 12)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1878-1886 (Box 13)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1887-1898 (Box 14)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1899-1944 and undated. (Box 15)
  - Printed Materials (Box 15)
  - Pictures (Box 15)
  - Account Volumes, 1861-1904 (Box 16)
  - Account Volumes, 1905-1920 (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous Volumes (Box 17)
  - Medical Notebook and Account Book, 1855-1866 (Box 18)
  - Medical Records for the 11th Virginia Cavalry (1863-1865) (Box 18)
  - Account Book, 1867-1870 (Box 18)
  - Sunday School Records (Box 18)
  - Wesleyan Catechism (Box 18)
  - Blair's Pocket Therapeutics (Box 18)
  - Physician's Handy Memorandum Book (Box 18)
  - The Taylor Pocket Case Book (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Writings and Volumes (especially concerning medical topics) (Box 18)
  - Volume, 1867-1873 (Volume F:6478)
  - Volume, 1871-1881 (Volume F:6479)
  - Volume, 1872-1880 (Volume F:6596)
  - Volume, 1873-1877 (Volume F:6597)
  - Volume, 1879-1886 (Volume F:6599)
  - Volume, 1882-1890 (Volume F:6600)
  - Volume, 1888-1892 (Volume F:6601)
  - Volume, 1901-1905 (Volume F:6602)
  - Volume (Volume L:6880)
  - Volume (Volume L:6471)
  - Volume (Volume L:6595)
  - Volume (Volume L:6598)
  - Volume (Volume M:6466)
  - Volume (Volume M:6594)